okay good morning I'd like to go
straight into a meditation while you
guys are while your mind is fresh okay
so please get ready to meditate what's
the first step the Buddha says turn off
your cell phone please turn off your
cell phone it's very okay so we're gonna
go through the lions dance meditation
and was it has five great parts it was
taught by Buddha in about three
different sutras and Maitreya taught it
to a Sangha so many of you have been
practicing in for the last year I think
we've been teaching it at the alarm room
retreats for about a year and it has
five great parts and we've only reached
through two parts and in this week we'll
do the third in the fourth part and I
wrote it out for you and it's in your
it's in you it's in a book there
somewhere yeah so this parts called
over-the-top Tokyo getting ensign via
the Granton Tama summer party so we'll
just start if you do the whole thing it
takes about an hour so we're gonna do it
in pieces so we'll do a big piece this
morning cuz morning time you're fresh
and then you'll be working on it during
your personal retreat okay all right so
here we go some of you have been
practicing it and I prefer that you
learn one of the five parts and then you
do it for a couple months and then you
learn the next part you do that for a
couple months so but I'm not gonna hold
up the people who have been doing it so
we will do the third and fourth parts
which is called to go to means top and
gell means to go over the top which is
why the lady's jumping over a stick okay
all right so here we go then when you
meditate in a group it's much more
powerful and it's also much more
distracting when you make north blow
your nose now okay surrender
so in this meditation which is called
lions dance singer vision betta or
[Music]
singing gimble number gimble it's the
first step is to immediately follow a
noise in the room so it could be the air
conditioner it could be small noises
from other meditators it could be your
children in the next room it could be
garbage trucks outside in New York City
so we'll start with a noise in the room
rather than counting your breath or
practices like that we go straight to a
listening to some sound in this room and
what will go slow when you have time
it's good to do about 20 breaths on each
step
now please go to the beating of your
heart which is represents the first form
realm level we can also call it the
world of beauty which is the meaning of
form realm Rupa da to observe your heart
beating if you're by yourself in your
home you can try to hear the heart being
especially inside your ear but in a
group usually there's too much noise to
do that and you can just feel the
sensation of the heart beating in your
chest
the idea is that we are drilling down to
a deeper point of focus and each step
involves a gotcha
which means rejecting something else so
we are the guck job for the first level
is the sound of the air-conditioner or
the garbage trucks outside and we
rejected and we got drill drill down
deeper to the sound of our heart or the
feeling of our heart beating and we
leave behind the noise in the room we
can't hear that noise anymore it's too
loud and we go to the heartbeat which is
more quiet
now we'll go deeper more quiet then now
the gotcha
or what we want to reject or leave
behind is the beating of the heart from
the outside so we drop the outside
beating at the heart and we enter the
second form realm level world of beauty
and we go inside the heart and we leave
behind the outer world which is more
noisy so now imagine you're sitting
inside the chamber of your heart and you
can feel the heart beating around you
the walls of the chamber are beating but
now you're inside the heart and you have
left behind the outer world form realm
level two
now sitting inside of the chamber of the
heart feeling it beat around us it's
it's normal no it's it's quieter and and
it's normal and now we're going to go
deeper so that feeling of sitting inside
the heart becomes a a gotcha something
we want to draw something we want to
leave behind we want to go deeper then
you imagine that still inside the dark
chamber of the heart now the hardest
inside the heart and it's beating far
away maybe maybe five or six meters away
and it's small and you have lost your
connection with it you are still in the
middle of the heart it's dark it's quiet
but now the beating of the heart is a
little bit far away distant still inside
the heart and there's a feeling of
neutral feeling you you are no longer so
connected to the heart it's pretty far
away and you're just observing it from
inside the heart in the darkness then
it's quiet and it's it's a little bit
away from you this is a form realm world
of beauty level three
now inside that quietly beating heart
which is separated from you you see a
single crystal of sugar a single grain
of sugar you can also use a diamond and
you go down towards the crystal deeper
drilling deeper into the heart and you
imagine that you become smaller and
smaller and then you can even see a
little door on the side of the crystal
and you open it and you all of you goes
inside the crystal like a pretty
comfortable room and you close the door
and you imagine that you're in a silent
chamber inside a single grain of sugar
or diamond tiny and it's very quiet and
you are meditating comfortably inside
this single tiny point deep within your
heart fourth form realm level something
Sheba
now we move up to the formless realm the
world beyond the physical and the first
one is called nam kata and now we expand
the mind we are still inside the sugar
crystal but the mind expands like a
ocean as wide as the ocean so I like to
imagine the ocean between China and
America and a vast wide ocean and the
surface of the ocean is very very quiet
like a lake or a pond and my mind is
spreading as wide as the ocean still
inside the crystal
it helps to think it's budding to the
left and to the right the mind itself
and it might help you to picture ripples
starting at the center of the ocean
maybe at Hawaii and spreading to the
horizon and beyond the horizon so
sometimes I like to drop a pebble in the
center of the ocean still inside the
crystal and the ripples are passing
towards the horizon further and further
and my mind is wide open to the sky like
a ocean okay go ahead you can drop the
pebble if you like
now second formless level we the ocean
becomes a Gupta it's too noisy and we
want to go deeper more quiet and we want
the mind to be more open and we want the
mind to expand further and further so we
imagine that the mind is like a light my
awareness is like a light and from where
I'm sitting which is still inside the
crystal in the middle of the ocean vast
ocean opened to the sky now my the light
of my awareness will expand like a ball
and it will go as if I turned on a light
the light will go not not just left and
right but it will go up to the sky and
beyond the sky all the way to the Sun
then beyond the Sun to each of the
planets and beyond the planets and then
to other stars and beyond the other
stars and continue a giant ball of
awareness it clear like water expanding
throughout all of space personally I'd
like to imagine that if there are
countless beings in the universe then
there must be other people doing this
meditation right now on some other world
and my expanding ball of awareness clear
water like awareness catches up with
Daris and
the two balls spread to each other and
then we both continue on so in a way
your mind is expanding to every mind in
the universe so I like to imagine that
I'm turning on a light in the middle of
my head and then that clear water like
light starts to expand in all directions
quickly beyond this planet to touch all
the other minds of the universe second
formless realm level called Nam Jie
infinite awareness
very open very free very happy very very
expanded the mind feels very happy and
clear
now that infinite mind becomes a gotcha
something too loud too noisy we want to
go even more quiet and now it's time to
turn the mind off it's called chiyomi
third formless room level and imagine
that you are just shutting off your mind
the mind turned off no more noise
feelings going through the mind or no
more thoughts so just pretend you're
turning your mind off like a light and
then everything's totally quiet silent
if thoughts come out if feelings come
out confront them fight them turn them
off so part of your mind is watching to
see if any thoughts come up in the mind
which is turned off
forth formless realm level and then
we'll take a break
it's called do she may do shame amen at
the third formless realm level we turned
off our mine and we tried to block the
small thoughts and feelings now at the
fourth formless realm level
traditionally we allow the thoughts to
come and go we allow the feelings to
come and go because it's more quiet it's
more silent if we don't attach to them
we don't pay attention to them we just
let them go so again we'll turn off the
mine but this time if thoughts come
through the mine we let them gather like
clouds in the sky and then we let them
dissolve like clouds in the sky and we
don't attach to them forth formless room
level do shame and do shame a mean very
very quiet
now please follow three long slow
exhales in your mind don't move don't
open your eyes follow three long exhales
and then slowly open your eyes and I
like to take a stretch oh you can drink
something when you're here in the desert
you have to drink a lot okay and it it
makes the class more interesting because
you have to go to the bathroom
so my mom my stepmother had her 90th
birthday recently she's been here she's
a big supporter of diamond mountain for
20 years mmm
she she does yogurt still she does yoga
with her and she walks three times a day
for for an hour three times a week sorry
three miles and she's amazing she's
still doing business and she's my
investment person so anyway we had her
90th birthday and she invited us to the
hotel on the beach small cheap hotel but
right on the beach so you can walk to
the beach and my brother said oh we're
gonna go surfing right I'm like okay and
because we used to surf a lot and so I
was in China and Taiwan and I thought I
better start exercising in the water
because I would die surfing so I went
with me and Stanley and John and Scott
almost every day we went swimming in the
hotel pool and it's very boring not like
surfing you know you just swim to the
other side and then you talk about
fundraising then you swim to the other
side talk about schedule and and then if
you want to go surfing you gotta do many
kinds of backstroke breaststroke
freestyle puppy dogs you have to do many
kinds of because the wave will push you
under and
you have to you have to know many ways
to swim so we tried every kind of
swimming but it's boring and it's not
surfing okay it's just to get ready for
surfing because if you don't do it you
will have a bad time when you go surfing
right so these four levels of the
formula and the four levels of the
formulas room and the air conditioner
which is the desire room so nine levels
right these are called warm up these are
not meditation they're just swimming
laps in the hotel pool because you want
to go surfing you see I mean so it's
very very famous that some people got
stuck in the hotel pool and they never
went surfing especially the third
formless room level it's very famous
when you turn your mind off some people
thought oh this must be emptiness so
they stopped there in the hotel pool and
they never go to the surfing sea so the
idea is these are all different ways to
sharpen your meditation skills and
they're just exercises they're not
surfing they're not the real thing so
after you do the desire realm then for
former models for formulas remember most
nine levels then you start the real
meditation then you go surfing okay so
don't stop in the pool okay there's no
content yet there's just technique
you see we're just exercising the
meditation muscle in different ways you
know and it's not it it won't help you
in your life the karmic scene you make
is it's just kind of a pleasant thing it
won't change your life you see so we are
just
exercising and never stop there don't
don't sit in the pool you never go in
the ocean you see I mean so these are
just exercise but they're very important
exercise and Buddha taught them alright
anybody gonna tell me why it's called
why is it called form realm or nowadays
I think that the translation might be
better if we call it world of beauty but
why is it called that anybody wanted to
see why are those first four called
formal yes yeah good if that's all you
do if you just stay in the pool your
whole life a lot first of all you get
wrinkled everywhere no just kidding yeah
because you're not having your normal
negative thoughts you will be born in a
world of beauty so form Rupa in in this
meditation formal means world of beauty
so you will be born into a place called
the the world of beauty and everybody
there looks like Iron Man and spider-man
and Superman and Wonder Woman
really in fact I believe that the movie
makers came from farm realm rebirth last
time and they still remembering what
people look like there and how strong
they are and how they can fly and
they're super beautiful and okay so it
but then you die there's and you your
bones and your dust and then you go to
hell okay so not a not a good place to
stop you know you go to a better you go
to a beautiful realm because because
you're meditating so much in the pool
that you don't have time to be jealous
of other people or
angry or upset or as we normally do okay
so it's just good luck and then you
temporarily you go to a nice place you
get to be Iron Man for a couple years
and then you use up all your good karma
and then you always go to the hell
realms okay not a don't stop in the pool
okay
why formless realm why the last four are
called formless realm meditations no you
already give an answer let the older
people say something why why do you go
for Miss room yeah no more gross form
you still have startled prana you still
have Chi I you in that sense you still
have a physical basis but but you're
basically a mental person you just live
in the head and it's very very very
pleasant it's like being on it's like
smoking marijuana all day I guess okay
judging from my friends who do that yeah
they seem like that they don't have any
activity they don't do anything they
they can't have any ideas they just kind
of hey man so that's like formless realm
beyond the physical
it means beyond physical okay so if you
stop in the pool that's the two choices
and that's why they're given those names
that's why they're I have those names
because if that's all you do then when
you die you will go to one of those
places temporarily and then you're good
at harems okay so not a place to stop
and we want to we want to go tuna -
surfing
okay so surfing is called coping yome
joke okay say cockpit
yum Juke dopamine stopping stopping
cessation stopping okay and Maria was
asking me what what kind of stopping
because I guess there's two words in
Russian for stopping so traditionally
it's called stopping meditation coping
your job because you stop your wrong
idea about things so you don't think the
pen is coming from the pin if you stop
thinking that the pen comes from the pen
and you realize that it comes from you
then you are you are doing stopping
meditation then that's a cessation the
stopping means you stop your belief that
the thing is coming from itself that's
why it's called stopping meditation okay
go pin Yong Jun so we're gonna do a go
pin your jungle okay that's the surfing
all right and after that you can do a
Wheel of Life meditation and that's like
lying on the beach after surfing and
enjoying the Sun okay all right those
are the two goals and surfing and lying
on the beach okay and my trailer said
Dennis and I'm ding ding ding engine on
young shooting a tangent Luke turned on
Lu me to not operate a very famous we
have to memorize and in the monastery he
says dear dear your desire realm which
is like the ground floor of our European
hotel because in Europe they call the
second Florida first floor you don't
know how many times I wander around the
lobby looking for my hotel room because
they say you're on the first floor but
the first floor is the second floor ok
so Lobby is desire realm air conditioner
then the first floor is the first form
room for four floors and then there's
four formulas room floors and I like to
parrot to them what's this hotel called
premier palace hotel in Kiev Ukraine
where we often have our programs there
and it's a great example because on the
9th floor counting European Way there's
a great American breakfast with a in
stunning view of Kia right you teach
there Peter and Maria they teach tasty
either a lot and congratulations for
that and then you can go down the ninth
floor and it's very secret you have to
go down some weird corridors and then
there's a huge American breakfast so for
me and Scott this is the ultimate goal
is the ninth floor
okay so ninth floor is like surfing its
ninth florists cessation meditation
stopping meditation emptiness meditation
and then if you want for dessert you can
do a dependent origination meditation
and then this is a four-course meal okay
that's called troop cheek-to-cheek in
meditation in the study of meditation
it's called to cheek-to-cheek means
truth means offsprings like a baby
caris called a bar to a baby rabbits
counter rebound - okay you just add true
and the color coil do you know the
colloquial it changes its poo goo goo
goo goo goo is to go
it means kid so this meditation has five
babies true okay we just did half of the
first baby we did half of part one we
just finished half of part one there's
four more parts four and a half more
parts we didn't do yet okay so it's sort
of a grand meditation that really you
can do it for three four years and get
good at it you know and it's good to
learn it in pieces and to get good at
the first eight floors and they're in
the lobby and then go on okay
so I'm going to describe the stopping
meditation okay
and I think recently in Taiwan we found
a good way to describe it
so if you have a partner wife husband
boyfriend girlfriend I don't know about
you I'm a little jealous I don't have to
be too jealous because my partner is
really beautiful and devoted and but in
my life since I was 16 I've been in
jealous relationships I know what
they're like
and it's very unpleasant because you're
always paranoid and so imagine that you
come home early from work and you walk
in the apartment or the and your partner
is sitting there like this you know and
they see you and then they're like oh hi
you're early you know and they take the
phone and they kind of hide it behind
them you know and you're like who are
you texting you know in the old days in
my house when I was a kid when I was a
teenager we just had one phone and then
you know four brothers with four
girlfriends trying to use one phone
email and it was always unpleasant and
then my mom we asked my mom we didn't
have money we asked my mom can we have
an extension phone so that means I can
sit in my bedroom and talked to my
girlfriend without talking in the
kitchen and everybody hears what I'm
saying
so this but they're connected so my
brother is always in the kitchen you
know
and then you can hear if you're a
teenager your ears are good you know you
can hear this that's when they pick up
the extension you know they say are you
on the lam yeah you shouldn't talk like
that to your girlfriend
shut up then it later it became
cellphones right and now people can do
it alter it very easily you know they
can text to some boyfriend or girlfriend
that their husband doesn't know about or
their wife doesn't know about so you
come home and your partner's like and
then they then they're like this you
know and and you say well where you're
texting and they're like oh there's
nobody then you get really uncomfortable
you know and you're like hmm what's
going on then you get paranoid
many people get jealous jealousy creates
misperception right so you think oh they
they must have a girlfriend and must
have a boyfriend then they take a shower
right and the phone is in the on the
table so naturally you don't like it and
you don't feel comfortable but you you
can't stop yourself you're like who who
are they're texting because you have
this whole picture in your mind of
somebody they met on the train last week
and they had a conversation and and they
were talking like hitting on each other
you know me and Veronica went to a my
stepmom took us to a play she went to
the bathroom some guy tried to take her
out and she came back she said I think I
just started yeah I'm like what where is
he
she's like he said he wants to get to
know me and I said no it doesn't
against a bad feeling right so you want
to check your partner's phone you know
you're checking it and you check the
time when you came home
what's the messages from this time and
and then it says there's a message from
Amazon or Alibaba and it says your
secret birthday gift for your wife is
it's delivered it's sent from Ali Baba
it will come this beautiful coat that
you bought for your wife is for her
birthday secret birthday present so he
was happy about the present that he
bought you
and he wasn't texting any girlfriend he
was happy because he got he found the
coat that he wanted for you and that's
why he had that big stupid smile on his
face and then all at that moment the
feeling you have and the picture you
have in your mind of the other has the
other boyfriend or the other girlfriend
the whole story that you wrote in your
mind for one hour two hours the whole
thing goes you know and that's gotcha
okay that's perfect gotcha okay my god
because the nature of gotcha the nature
of a self existent thing is it gives you
emotions it gives you anger it gives you
jealousy you see and it's all thing it's
not true it doesn't exist at all
okay it's some story you wrote in your
mind and when you check your husband's
phone he's ordering you a birthday
present
then suddenly the gotcha okay that's
gotcha something that wasn't there just
goes and it just disappears okay so
that's the goal when we get to surfing
okay we're going to explore things that
don't exist that give us all of our
negative emotions all our strong
emotions anger jealousy desire we're
gonna realize poof
it was never there okay so when we go to
the ninth floor the American breakfast
the surfing is to explore how things
that we got so excited about weren't
even there got it
okay so we're going to when we reach the
ninth floor that's what we're gonna do
and that's called coping Yangcheng
stopping what are we stopping the idea
that your husband had a boyfriend okay
how real was it not enough okay
you're stopping something that was never
real anyway got it okay that's go pinion
Jim you got to understand you're not
stopping your anger that exists you're
not stopping your jealousy that exists
you're stopping what caused the anger
and what caused the jealousy which is a
guy who never existed or a woman who
never existed okay got it
it was just alibaba or amazon got it
okay
so you gotta get that feeling I was
wrong there was nothing there I was all
upset for nothing and and every upset
feeling you ever had in your life was
the same all of them they were thinking
about something that wasn't there every
time you get upset not just this time
okay and that exercise of blowing up
people you're upset it is called surfing
okay that's the real goal so don't waste
your time in the elevator go have the
American breakfast go surfing though
don't do laughs in the stinky hotel pool
in the chemical water you know go out in
the nice fresh saltwater and beautiful
sun line and stuff okay that's when I
was 25 now it's kind of like
okay all right so let's take a break
PP break and when we come back well well
do a little bit of the America of the
American breakfast and by the way that
that's only part of the first round took
its first round we have to do five
rounds we have to learn five rounds all
right okay let's start some people had
some questions about the meditation I
think Vimala would like to start with a
question so let's do a microphone so
everybody can hear and please try to
talk into the mic like some people hold
the mic like this and tongue try to try
to talk into the mic so everybody can
hear me okay we'll do some questions
about the meditation thank you thank you
Lama so when you're going into the heart
chakra and you're going deeper and
deeper into the heart chakra into the
forum realm and this feeling of like
becoming a kind of a solid form and then
you come out inside the heart chakra and
you go out infinitely in your touching
infinite beings it's the formless realm
so I was wondering is there a connection
between the form and the formless and
the Rupa kya the the enjoyment bodies in
boga and the emanation bodies is there
some connection between the samsaric
form and formless and then going into
the Buddha baths yeah good question I
think there's a big connection from for
me especially when I do the ocean and
the space then I think it I feel like
it's sort of preparing me for the day
when I reach Buddha headquarters
as the newest buddha and they assign a
planet to me i always see me and v-- we
get assigned a planet to take care of
and so i feel like i already have
experience with outer space so actually
i I do feel that it sets up the seeds
for the different Buddha bodies and I
you know it's important I think too
there are very few teachings that were
specifically the same between our Buddha
Gautama and the next Buddha Maitreya but
this teaching was repeated by both of
them independently you know and so I
think there must be some big
significance to planting seeds for your
body for your Buddha bodies from even
from the laps in the pool okay I agree
yeah any other question I have a
question from the live stream okay cool
this is from Lucy in Canada cool she
asks what when you do this step inside
the heart with the grain of sugar
crystal I'm a bit afraid to create
something wrong in my heart like and
what would I do at that point yeah it's
a good question so traditionally you
know especially the long term meditators
and we have a few in here can if you did
a three-year retreat can you stand up
Connie John Earl yeah
yeah so you have seven three retreats
which is unusual in one room and when
you do a long-term retreat you kind of
want to avoid too much going on in your
heart chakra because it's a very
vulnerable place in your spiritual body
and you can easily get unbalanced you
can get nervous or and you might feel it
this week okay in your own cabin if
you're used to living in Beijing or
Shanghai Guangzhou and suddenly you're
out in the desert by yourself and
there's all kinds of interesting
creatures walking around and too many
stars and so you can feel a little bit
nervous in your heart so you yeah when
you're meditating personal retreats it's
good not to do too much inside the heart
and the antidote is to drop the
meditation to your navel chakra so you
drop it to the level of your bellybutton
more towards the back okay so when they
say navel chucker they don't mean name
off so you don't meditate on this little
hole you go you go around at the same
height to the back and just in front of
the spine and you bring the meditation
there so you can do it there if you
start to feel nervous at the heart and
I'll tell you a funny thing which is not
funny when you're in a long retreat if
you go too low you won't be able to
poopoo so if that happens raise it up a
little bit okay but if you feel nervous
like your breath is too fast and your
heart's beating too fast and your hands
are shaking a little bit in a in your
personal retreat then moot drop it to
the navel chakra
any other question there's another
question from the live stream okay this
is from the great Aaron Chad up in
Sedona Arizona and she says thank you
for teaching Geshe my question is about
the fourth formless realm in the lion's
dense I'm wondering if this is what
other traditions might call Shama table
meditation there's a lot of confusion
about meditation practices there's many
many confuse you know what they call the
puffs
Vipassana for for example I I did it in
1975 with Goenka who founded it and I
spent 10 days with him in deep retreat
and there was a there were 50 Tibetan
monks with us and and we did it for 10
days and you know I I was very young I
didn't know about meditation and and I
learned a lot and the most at that time
the most important part of it was to
watch your breath and and so that would
be the elevator that would be swimming
laughs you see so there's no content to
it which would cause you to become
enlightened it would just make you more
peaceful or calm for a while and so
later I learned it's not Vipassana
Vipassana is a pali word which is spoken
sanskrit it's like he thought like they
knew in indigo you the south in America
and people thought a lot like
and the words are a little bit tight so
Sanskrit became spoken for a while and
then people
it's called poly and it's kind of like
slang and so the world the world word is
Vipassana and not by personal and then
it it doesn't mean watching your breath
so it just got some confusion it got
some confusion after the Buddha died
until the Gardena 700 years there was a
period of confusion and that's when the
abhidhamma was the main Buddhist school
and I spent 12 years studying epidermis
so we take it very seriously I memorized
the first half of the book na Pournami
Gucci I want to heal and you know I'm
not angry but then on the cleaning no no
not like that
okay but but it's mistaken okay it's not
high school and so those traditions came
out of done so it's good to know them
and it's good to understand them and
it's good not to swim laps for your
whole life you know it's better to learn
to surf okay but it it doesn't hurt it's
just that you shouldn't stop in the
elevator and you will never get a good
breakfast okay it doesn't help you that
much
it's just exercise one more question
any Vivian Houseman yeah
Thank You Kara my question is for this
meditation and luxury digestion General
Quarters shall rock over me I should so
Jeremy son - AHA - go on the don't see
who shake everyone's hand dad I don't
see nomination amore boyfriend - hey
changin salad now will change Hudson see
just say attention without the TV
station secret Sara nice option you may
13 sit down join your true soul by
holding a shield before you talk about
this meditation it's very important to
know that we should have a very high
motivation talk about that kind of high
motivation that one part of your mind
will stop so because I'll check my life
and I found that sometimes I found
myself that I'm not I forgot things so
many that's because something you know
after something wrong in this meditation
so it stopped that part of my yeah good
question
so the Karma of staying in the elevator
it's the seed you plant by kind of
smoking marijuana meditation in
meditation you know just like some
people like to go home and drink a beer
every night and they don't get drunk and
they don't fight but they're like and if
I just meditate to feel good or to feel
peaceful the Karma of that the seed
plants in my mind is to be forgetful or
or to be not be able to think clearly
and so Vivian's asking if I do the
elevator with a low motivation and you
know I kind of get stuck in the elevator
then chemically in my planting seeds to
be forgetful like you lose your keys and
you lose your cell phone and you don't
remember what you're supposed to do
today
Alison has to send you email you guess
how you forgot to do this thing and yeah
I think it's possible but but I I think
the general law Miriam does people who
come to the mom room regularly you don't
have to come to all of them it's too
many you'll get fired from your job and
your family will divorce you but but
those who come to know Miriam I think
you understand the goal and you
understand the purpose of what we're
doing so I think you know like what
you're doing in Guangzhou you're
organizing thousands of people that
motivation is to help the whole city of
Guangzhou and I don't think you ever
lose it I think you can have a bad day
when you're just thinking about yourself
but I don't think it's possible for you
to keep coming to my room and you don't
think about the reason why we're coming
here is to help the world so I don't
think you have to worry about it it's
probably just getting old
[Music]
right there you made for can tell you
about it but I don't worry too much
about it it'll it won't stay you know
him those are old seeds and you are
burning them so I don't personally I
find my mind becoming sharper as I you
know every year weird weird things
strange things like I remember Buddhism
classes I had when I was 20 or something
very clearly so I think your mind will
get sharper
as you go there okay so I kinda wanted
to we have about an hour left at this
class and I wanted to kind of give you
the plan for the week okay so there's a
couple thing a couple of goals I have
one is while we're fresh especially in
the morning we'll spend a lot of time on
meditation and I'd like you I've never
taught the third and fourth parts of the
Alliance dance so you guys are the first
people in the world to do it this week
and and we'll do part three in part four
okay we have already done half a part
one but the other half the other parts
are faster so I'd like to do parts three
and four with you
and then I would like you to do it in
your personal retreat the three days
personal retreat and I would like you to
do it for the next few months okay
because then when I do part five you are
ready okay and those of you who haven't
been working on it like I know I taught
it in Germany for example or Vienna and
you guys should be practicing it because
then when I teach the next part you're
ready for the next part you see I mean
so you gotta have the foundation so if
you haven't had the first few parts just
and we did it in New York just it's okay
you'll have to catch up okay but you
have to work hard between retreats okay
on the meditation then then it's much
more exciting to do the next part
because you're your foundation is there
okay
so we'll spend a lot of time on the lion
stance its I gave you a reading Tim told
me I wrote the numbers wrong just I
missed numbered something but don't
worry about it
I think around number 20 and it does it
twice so but that's it that's a nice
thing and we'll do that all week and
then we'll continue
with the long room long room is a
there's two tracks in Buddhism there's a
Geshe track and there's a long room
track so you can either become a mom can
take the Getty track and then you study
the five grade books for 20-25 years all
day and if you don't have time for that
traditionally in Tibet you would do long
mem track and then and the monks also do
long rim track but they do it during
vacation time then big Lamas come and
teach Norman you know it's kind of like
a desert so my main track it's really
the same information as the Geshe track
but it's not as detailed and it's more
it's more focused on meditation so long
Lim is this similar information but it's
more emphasis on meditation using it in
meditation geishas don't use it the
gadgettrak in meditation that much
they'll do their meditations are largely
from lovren okay
so if you want to be a meditation
teacher or something like that you
should know the mom room okay so what do
young men will do the next part of the
lung room we have reached a section
about suffering okay
especially different kinds of suffering
of human beings okay so we'll be it's
kind of a depressing week and it's
supposed to make you sad so you want to
keep going to get out of the suffering
but first you have to learn the
suffering and according to the alarm
room we are all suffering three kinds of
suffering right number one is called do
yoga dunya which is
suffering a pain you know like the
classic example Senshi headache backache
okay
obvious pain okay then the second kind
of pain given to me which is one
what's the century classical example a
dinner at Cucina Rustica right like a
really nice dinner because it will
change you know you will get hungry
after a while so it's it's really not
pleasure it's like another kind of it's
disguised pain while you eating the
dinner and having before you've been
hungry you are getting older
okay and if you go to enough dinners you
will be in the nursing home you see so
during the pleasure you're also getting
older and your body is starting to fall
apart
okay those of us what do we talk about
when you hit 65 I'll tell you we talk
about our doctors yeah I need doctor Wow
meaning what
yeah they give me Arif okay so you bad
even while you do yoga even while you
meditate your body is getting older so
we're going to study on that this week
we're gonna continue to the love him so
my goal is to teach the whole lung room
nor the luck jump which is called a gift
of liberation stuffed into your hands
like the Lama goes take it you know
here's Buddhahood you know so that's the
name of the book I think it's the
greatest book ever written
it's about 500 pages 400 500 in the
Tibetan and the goal we had a goal of
finish it in 10 years and we're on
schedule we're about eight years through
eight and a half something like that
we're not far from the end now we're
about two years from the end it's been
29 we this is the twenty-ninth routine
it's it's cool that we all survived and
we're still going
so we have about eight more classes then
my strategy in the beginning was I
taught the meditation section first I
went to the end of the book and I taught
the meditation section because we were
going to meditate during all the rooms
so those of you who were there in
Prescott and Phoenix we started at the
end of the book and we did the
meditation section then we went back to
the beginning so you could use the
meditation to meditate on a lemon but
then I thought when we get to the end
and we reached the meditation section
which we already did we'll skip tatanka
paws long room because this long room
doesn't spend much time on meditation
and emptiness because tsongkhapa
spent half his book so so God has 500
pages on meditation and emptiness so my
grand plan was teach the meditation
section from the gift of liberation then
do the whole gift of the rest and then
at the end for dessert we did some kapa
on on schemata and Vipassana direct
perception emptiness and so this this
book will take eight more retreats and
then if we do dessert that will take 20
more retreats we have 28 where half a -
we finished 29 we had 28 to go now my
idea is the reason one of the reasons I
thought the long room was my teacher
taught it to me three times his teacher
wrote it down his teachers teacher gave
the teaching so he had the red lineage
holder you are for generation your
fourth generation so it was taught by
poppin cream pitcher it was written down
by to Diamond person who edited it for
20 years and it's the greatest book in
the Tibetan
and then my teacher taught at three
times for 30 years and now I'm teaching
it next one is you you have to teach it
so I have a plan I have a new plan since
we have eight retreats left I'm going to
start reviewing the whole thing also
okay so part of this week every class
will start to review the whole thing so
by the time you reach the end of the
gift of liberation you will have
reviewed the whole thing my motivation
for reviewing it is I want you to teach
it okay and so far I didn't do homeworks
and I didn't do examinations because to
be honest I didn't have time because I'm
so busy and Gordo and other places so my
dream is to review it with you straight
a thing that I call it him
you gotta put up the first in him even I
made a new word in English Stanley and
Allison came to me they said what we
have to translate this this reading is
not what's Edom
I said Edom is a new word I invented it
what's it mean it's called idea image
idea image so it's a picture pneumonic
something that will trigger your memory
of a subject okay so I'm choosing
pictures that will remind you of one of
the great topics of the lamrim here's
the first one okay so that's the picture
of the author who gave the teaching
problem cover in future and I want you
to use the pictures as a study tool to
become a teacher
okay long known teacher so that's suffer
from a DCI teacher for example okay
alignment teacher is a different thing
and I want you to look at the picture
and I'll review with you starting this
week and
review for two years we'll just review
for two years
how many idioms will there be 500 okay
there will be 500 we have to finish 60
this week you have 8 more long memory
treats we have to review 60 ideas this
week if you're going to pass it on to
the next generation
okay so this is my way to test you then
I have another idea you want to put up
that image of the ACI teacher training
thing which I sent you this morning it's
a PDF of two pages it's just a black and
white two-page thing I sent you this
manner you'll find it anyway I have an
idea we would like to start at ACI
teacher training like the DCI teacher
training the DCI teacher training which
the the bosses or read of the college in
Sedona and they've been going for just
over a year now for me the magical
moment was in Taipei and we had 3,000
participants we had 3,000 people in the
room and we had 31 teachers and they
were most of them were trained at the
college and I got all these people
telling me these teachers are really
good you know I had a lot of people tell
me these teachers are really really good
you know and I've been trying to teach
teachers for 30 years and I felt
spectacularly but a week got it together
or eaten Scott mostly a read
they have a good training it's a tough
training and they are producing really
good teachers so I'd like to thank her
it isn't yeah but so anyway I would like
to do we would like to do an AC on
teacher training what's a demonstrator
AC on DCI a CI what DC is meant to be
not religious okay and for example
earlier this year we went to Kazakhstan
and we taught a thousand Muslim people
in one night
DCI so this is the great ideas no what's
the name of this thing
hang on sorry hang on just a second
[Music]
you know and
oh you're right I did give you the wrong
one
Yeah right dad
oh okay
okay it's called a CI teacher training
okay uh was I talking about
yeah so anyway I was so happy with
what's happening with the DCI teachers
that we would like to train a statue so
what's the difference between AC and DC
I this is meant for everybody in the
world and it's especially meant for
business people professional people and
it doesn't matter if they want to be
Buddhist or not you know many of them
for example all the Muslim 1000 Muslim
people that we taught in Kazakhstan none
of them want to be Buddhist they're not
interested they have their own religion
they're happy with it and I'm happy that
they're happy and everyone should do
what their parents did and that's okay
you don't want to get married in a
Christian Church if you're Buddhist and
you don't want to get married at a
Buddhist church if you're Muslim
so that's okay right
so when DCI is trying to teach the great
ideas of Asia to normal people so they
can be successful in their life in their
business in their family in their health
in their mental state and that we can
create some kind of peace in the world
so that's DCI it's extremely successful
it's kind of too successful and we are
we have invitations to many many
countries we can't go to we are
canceling many countries so we we really
need more teachers and I think the
colleges is very very exciting and it's
producing new teachers so fast that I
think we can meet the new countries that
need us you know so I'm excited about it
and I think it will go on for many years
and we have a dream to build a branch in
Europe and a branch in Asia
so we can train teachers in other
languages so that's DC I ACR is more
Buddhist okay it's spiritual it's for
people who are attracted to spiritual
things in DC I for example we don't talk
about what's going to happen to you
after you die or how can you become
Buddha it's not appropriate in DCI but
in a CI this is the beginning of a CI is
what's going to happen to you after you
die like and it's a big filter DC is a
big filter so a thousand people will
come to a talk at the Union Trade Center
in Singapore from the thousand people
100 people will come to DCI retreat to
go deeper from those hundred people ten
people will come to that month okay so
it's like a big filter so the people who
are deeply interested in spiritual
things they will end up here few people
out of you are out of twenty five
thousand people you are the ones who
came here so we need good ACI teachers
and we've been talking in many years how
can we teach a CI how can we create a CI
teachers and we have an idea which we're
working on with Jasmine because she did
such amazing job in Thailand
yeah she sings and she also does great
organizing 430 people came to the Long
Room in Thailand last time and she's
building every year she's good at
organizing lamb ribs so we we had an
idea we've been teaching a CI for 25
years 30 years
Hector's teaching it in New York for
many years like well we're trying to
think how to share a cell with more
people so we wanted to try something
it's called a meditation club sorry
meditation studio so when I wrote the
diamond cutter book in the book I said
maybe businesspeople should meditate at
the time it was very strange idea and
people loved it and the book sold many
many copies I don't know million copies
and many many people are but in the book
I said maybe people want to try yoga
also and my editor at doubleday which
was the biggest book company in the
world at the time they said take it out
take out the word yoga I said why they
said nobody does yoga put golf you know
I think the first edition said golf and
at that time there was one yoga studio
in New York now yoga studio is normal
everywhere in the world every everywhere
you go there's yoga studios and they're
actually based on the model of the first
New York yoga studio which was I think
the first major one with Stephen Mukti
so why you do an hour or why are you
doing hour and a half the exercises you
do everything the whole system how the
class is held we don't know but there's
a history to it and it started with a
few people
it started with three or four people and
they just said well how are we going to
teach you I don't know
let's get a big room Oh what do you want
to do let's give up Matt Matt what's a
mess you know and you think it's normal
now but at the time it was they just had
to create it because nobody was doing it
and even my editor didn't want me to put
yoga in the book you know now it's
millions of people aren't doing yoga
right so we think people want meditation
like that and when I went to the three
jewels in New York when I walk in the
door of their new studio which is
amazing because it has a coffee shop
when you walk in the door says
enlightenment studio and I was like wow
that's that's gotta be Hector you know
like I want to steal that enlightenment
so anyway we would like to build a chain
of like meditation studios and and then
you call it meditation people come from
meditation you teach them meditation you
have many levels of meditation and it
becomes normal like in China there's an
old tradition of clan club like all the
Wong's
in Singapore will start a club called
the Wong Club I've been there we we gave
talks there and it's a nice building
like century 21 in Shanghai or the club
in China Shenzhen
it's a nice it's like the Princeton Club
in New York and it's like five stories
there's a sauna there's a yoga room
there's meeting rooms
there's a nice Kevin you know tea you
can go for tea like real Chinese tea
service or they have nice food really
nice food so we would like to start
building things like that where business
people can go for meditation and they
get a massage and
do a sauna and they meditate and in the
backpack back room there's a DCI I'm
sorry a CI 36 course is going on in the
back room so if you like you can go to
the back room only the special people
and the other body learns to meditate
and be calm and relaxed and have a nice
talk with your friends and have a nice
tea and have a nice meal and do some
meditation together and then go back to
your job relaxed and fresh and
enlightened so anyway I thought Jasmine
should be in charge of that around the
world and so we've been working on that
because she's a business person also and
she knows how to borrow money and from
investors and build buildings and and so
but we need teachers we need teaching
stuff for those centers those studios so
you know so here's my idea you guys
ready yeah yeah here's my idea for we
had many meetings with Jing Mei and Tim
who are in charge of a CI in them in
America at the college building we have
an office there and this is what we
thought and we maybe change some things
but first is first level only meditation
guidance if that means you've finished
Adam Adam means idea image 500 pictures
if I put a picture in front of you you
can say yes this is the third obstacle
of meditation what is the third obstacle
meditation
huh what yeah good okay either you got
sleepy mind or busy mind okay in your
meditation then the picture happens to
be a wife who's excited - excited and
her husband next to her who's falling
asleep that's the image effect I chose
it this morning so that would be one of
500 images so you will take like I guess
you examination if you want to be
alarming meditation teacher you will
take an exam with 500 pictures and I'll
show you a wife who's too excited and
her husband sitting next to her who is
too sleepy and you're gonna tell me this
is meditation obstacle number three and
then you pass the test and you become a
meditation teacher lahrman meditation
teacher okay so we're gonna do those 500
pictures 60 at a time so this week we'll
do 60
okay I will review with you the first 60
which is about what 10% and then we do
it seven more times seven more retreats
okay if you cannot come to the next
retreat you're not going to get the
items for that retreat then you can talk
to Jasmine and you can or Tim or
jing-mei you will work it out to train
you for those you see I mean but then
each item will have the page number of
the Lamia so in Chinese and in English
the three-volume book so if you don't
remember why the wife is excited and why
the husband is sleepy you just go read
those two pages and you review from the
book okay so if you want to be alarmed
in meditation guide 500 items a 60 at a
time 8 retreats the next Avery treats
because after the 8th one we're done
with this book okay then you can be a
meditation
Longman meditation teacher okay and next
point you can do it personally or you
can do it professionally personally
means you teach your family or you teach
your friends and we have many teachers
like that around the world they are
teaching ACI to their friends and their
I think or read is teaching her mother
and it's very successful I don't know
how many levels she did 15 her mom who's
a boss of a hospital who runs a hospital
okay but she's secretly she's doing a CI
crisis okay so you can do it personally
you can be certified to teach small
groups in your living room or if you
want to teach professionally it's
tougher the certification is tougher
like Peter and Maria teaching in Europe
you know it's tougher to pass okay we'll
have more requirements okay and if you
want to teach online you need a
professional certification class okay
plus more because online teachers are
more they affect thousands of people
tens of thousands of people's so they
have to be better okay so there are
special professionals teachers okay
second kind of teacher and you have a
choice you can do one or you can do two
or you can do both
you can be super teacher okay so you
have choice you can do llamaron which is
more spiritual and more meditation okay
or you can do ACI courses which is gishy
okay 36 courses there are 18 foundation
courses and there are 18 advanced
courses okay you can go either one and
again you can do personal which is small
groups teach small groups you are
certified to teach to your friends and
their friends friends but not the
friends friends friends
okay and all you can do professional
which means you could teach at Jasmine's
meditation studio to you you see I mean
you have license to teach professional
professionally and then you you can do
online art okay next part in meditation
studio master that's teaching
professionally in a meditation studio in
in Beijing or Shanghai or Los Angeles or
New York or whatever and Hector we're
thinking he should build a second Center
in New York the first Center is
religious the meditation centers are not
religious they are for professional
people okay it's like a club private
club okay it's not religious and it and
we will ask the approval of the Chinese
government okay before we build them in
China okay
we will talk to the necessary people to
make sure it's over it's not religious
okay it's for professional people to
sharpen their mind and have good food
once a week some meditation studio
training
my idea is 12 concentrations
concentration means health peace of mind
creativity innovation leadership you
choose one you see that mean and you can
teach those meditations I like this
thing of Russia Russia will shoe tight
went down anyway you get these belts
right you go I did it for one year until
I broke my foot you get white belt then
you get yellow belt then you get green
belt then you get brown belt then you
get black belt then you get black belt
number two like round number three so I
thought we could have levels of
meditation training for professionals
professional business people like that
and then maybe companies will ask
we want to have that training in our so
the meditation studio would supply
meditation training to two companies and
I would like to call it meditation
teachers and not ACI teachers you see
there are meditation teachers they gotta
teach meditation accidentally they teach
a CI again understand next because
everybody likes a meditation teacher
okay so what I just talked about is
content
it's the lamrim or it's the AC I guess e
courses but what we learned at Diamond
Mountain by hard experience was it's not
enough to teach a teacher the content
you have to teach them other things also
or they are not a good teacher we we
made a mistake here so these are more
requirements okay first one is four legs
of the table for every other all the
meditation teachers will have to do the
four legs of the table number one is
content that's the 36 ACI courses or the
long M courses 500 image ideas or the
executive meditations for the for the
studios okay
that's content we are very very good at
content we are the best in the world
nobody comes close I don't think so
second is presentation some people know
the material but they don't know how to
teach they get up in the Obama okay so
will teach you not to be nervous
basically and or read has a fantastic
system for that so we're gonna ask her
to be advised this process third is
production which is Scott's grade skill
which is how do you do a program for 500
people you know yollie right in Taiwan
how do you how do you handle three
thousand people in a nursing
how do you market how do you how do you
finance it how do you keep the finance
it's like that it's not enough to be a
teacher and it's not enough to know your
content if you don't know how to rent a
room and get the people there you see
what I mean
so that's presentation then the first
part of it is professionalism which is
mainly two things number one you don't
hurt other people sexually or their
marriage or things like that you are
good behavior
second is financial you keep good
records you pay your taxes you're clean
your finances are clean your your
finances are correct and you're not in
debt okay so those are the four
principles that we teach
DCI teachers and we would like to use it
for the AC on teachers also number five
I put here design language study DCI has
a whole language which is like French or
something you have to learn it you know
like somebody says you have a two
husband's in the kitchen problem and
then everybody else is like what you
need the pen or you know you you need to
think about what's that called you
cannot guess these are all dc-9 language
you should learn it because when you
teach in the meditation studio you
probably have to use a lot of DCI
dialogue language okay so every I think
everyone in the ACI training should
learn a little bit of DCI right now in
the DCI training everybody learns the
ACI courses also and it's very good for
them
we have DCI teachers from Europe for
example who come to me they said I don't
want to be Buddhist I said yeah but
you're gonna study the ACI course I
don't ask you to become Buddhist you
don't have to be Buddhist but you have
to know the ancient books you have to
understand the ancient books you must
study the ASEAN course
if you're an ACI teacher you should be
able to speak the modern language which
is so successful for DCI the reason
3,000 people come is that we're not
talking about bodhichitta we're not
talking about Rupa kya dharmakaya
sambhogakaya there's no Sanskrit there's
no Buddhist words it's all seeds and pen
and four steps and stop oxen shim baka
okay so you need this language I think
number six continuing education units my
partner Veronica she's a massage
therapist legally she has to take a
course every year from which is approved
by the state of Arizona legally to be
licensed she has to come back once a
year and take it's like three days of
courses or she or she cannot practice
it's the same for lawyers it's the same
for doctors it's the same for
schoolteachers because you are you are
responsible for people's health and
happiness so they have to make sure you
are still training you still understand
you didn't get trained twenty years ago
and you forgot everything and you are
still teaching so every year you come
back and you you do review course like
that ACI MDC regular programs maybe you
come to a retreat in Mexico or time and
once a year just so we can see you we
make sure you didn't grow two heads like
that you review and deepen courses you
take deeper courses like we're going to
start in a garden in
Mexico much much deeper okay so you take
these special courses and then finally
the translators and we're fortunate
today we're going to have a talk by one
of the translators we have about twelve
people ten in Sedona studying how to
translate the ancient books and we have
about 81 in China studying how to
translate the ancient Chinese classics
and so we have about about a hundred
translators worldwide the ones in
Arizona are producing two thousand pages
of translation per year and we have a
plan to produce a hundred and eight
books the first one was finished two
days ago and it's ready to go to the
publisher it's the comic the only great
the only long commentary to the diamond
cutter cetera from Choni la Mer okay
so my idea is if you're gonna be an ACI
teacher you are studying these books you
are learning these books okay and it
went to four trans that book went for
translation yesterday into Chinese it's
half I finished in Spanish already and
we have Germans like we get this gonna
work on it right Rooskies like
Kondratiev so it base books will go to
them and they'll start translating them
into modern languages okay so you would
be involved with that
cool so those are your options
that to go back to the beginning of it
the first page the long name review will
start tonight okay we'll start the first
we'll start the first images of the 500
image ideas okay
Edom and we'll just go like that how we
do where we did
other training that you need like how to
present will probably do it at the
college in Sedona and we're talking
about although we're not clear yet maybe
we'll do the DCI teacher training and
then immediately do the ACI teacher
training after that and then the ACI
course that you study would be together
the DCI teachers and the ACI teachers
would study the ACI course together you
see I mean we just have to build a new
building and stuff like that but we're
not totally clearing that Jasmin's we're
working on that Tim and jing-mei Hector
who's gonna run those divisions we have
to decide if you're interested in
helping with this project which is more
religious more meditation it's
meditation oriented and I think most of
the people in this room you are kind of
like more lamrim than DCI you are you
you like this yeah but you you also like
Lamia
so if you are interested if your heart
is that kind of heart if you're
interested in the ACI training talk to
Jigme or Tim or Jasmine Jasmine will run
it globally especially the clubs and and
and talk to them okay we kind of need a
few business people to help to help
people who have business experience we
kind of need people in different
countries who have who have done you
know who have built businesses who
understand that okay so that's the plan
for this week it's not much
and we have half an hour and we're gonna
start the lamb rim we're going to go
back to the number okay and I I don't
know if you have the I guess I should
send you then latest that's good
actually I'm gonna start I'm going to
start with something which is not in the
text okay
the text mentioned the for ayah truth
okay so this is the first teaching that
the Buddha ever gave where dear part
time line yeah which Allison and Stanley
they visited our Sanskrit entries Center
in Varanasi and they went to visit the
Deer Park is 45 minutes from our entry
centers so if you ever want to go there
on a pilgrimage you can stay at the at
the entry center we have a nice
beautiful building there
we're building a second building as a
school and they are typing in the great
books of Sanskrit Buddha Buddhist books
which are very difficult to find and
vimana is doing a lot of great work to
find those and I think we should give
her a hand yeah
some nobody found the great books in
Sanskrit before a Buddhism and and her
team there they're working very hard on
Christina Casca's not here right oh
sorry
she's on the team - yeah so anyway that
was the first teaching of the Buddha was
he Tata for aya truth okay
and I that's the last thing we talked
about in the last moment and I would
like to review it okay so these are for
oh I thought it had 1115 sorry I have a
lot more minutes these are the first
teaching that Lord Buddha gave to whom
the five Tigers okay the mommy tiger and
her four babies okay how Daniel was the
most important one
do you remember what happened with
captain here before we had it recently
he was the king of culling huh yeah yeah
we had it in Taiwan yeah
the the main tiger mommy was the King of
Lanka who cut off the fingers of the guy
in the diamond cutter Sutra yeah okay
anyway so the for our truths are really
the foundation of all Buddhism and they
came up here in the lumber-room and I
wanted to go on a little side trip and
explain them because they don't get
explained very clearly very often the
word they are called Aria sutta right
they are called the Aria truths and so
early in the history of Western Buddhism
they missed translate the word Aria and
they said noble noble means very
respectable follows the rules pays their
taxes nice person and and that's a wrong
translation it's not the meaning of Aria
okay so don't so forget the word in
English Noble Truths Four Noble Truths
is not correct it's one of the big
traditional mistakes in Buddhism I can't
Dharma rumors
they're just mistakes okay so it's not
Noble Truths its Aria truth why is it
called aya truth it's because only a
person who has seen emptiness directly
understands the for truth directly okay
you can study them before that you can
learn about them before that but only an
ayah sees them directly okay only an
aria understands them directly and they
relate to the path of seeing so the
first time you see emptiness directly in
that day in those two or three hours you
have these four understandings and each
of the four has four parts so there are
sixteen okay there's called the sixteen
aspects of the fortress okay and there
are two ways to teach the fortress you
can teach them in the way that happen or
you can teach in the order that they
happen or you can teach them in the
order that they occur in your mind okay
and I'll explain the difference okay
anyone give me one of them
no fortress yeah pain suffering okay
that that's the first one okay pain
suffering especially getting all for
getting everything not being able to
surf anymore other tragedies like that
okay that's the first one what's the
second one yeah where does it come from
what's the source source of suffering
okay where does it come from okay that's
the second truth the third truth you can
stop it you can stop it okay fourth
truth yeah it's a path there's a path
okay there's a way okay there's a way to
stop it okay now that's the order in
which it occurs when you're thinking
about it but the actual order is what
which one of the four comes first the
source yeah first you have a source of
pain then you have pain then you follow
the pot and then you get to the end of
the path you see so there's two ways to
teach the fortress okay there's two ways
one is how do they actually happen in
time and then secondly how do they
happen in your thinking okay so
traditionally we teach them suffering
first okay because most people aren't
even aware that they are suffering okay
they are suffering and they don't know
they are getting there in the yoga class
they are exercising they feel pretty
good and they're dying and and then
suddenly they hit old age in their honor
freaked out or they get their cancer or
they get their heart attack and then
suddenly they discovered the truth of
suffering we had a student who lost her
husband recently in a restaurant he died
in a restaurant sitting next to her
unexpected
she came to me she said I just
understood the fortune
wow I just got the first one you know
all this time you've been teaching yes
she's been she's been studying for 15
years she said I just understood the
first turn you know first time so pain
okay suffering even if you're having a
good life which is unusual you're
getting older you will lose everything
DCO is kind of funny because we're
teaching people to get things that
they're gonna lose anyway then they you
have to come to the meditation studio
then they have to go to the bathroom you
see always so that's the idea
DCI is like the tunnel to the train or
something anyway and then the second one
is the source to classical divisions of
the source of pain to to to classical
yeah karma and negative emotions is the
current lingo yeah
karma and then the negative thoughts
that make you do karma anger to jealousy
desire
okay so conjunct Demba the source of
pain has two divisions karma and then
the negative thinking that makes you do
karma okay that's the source third one
the end of pain okay basically two
levels I think you can think of it that
way what to Nirvana and Buddhahood okay
Nirvana and Buddhahood
nope then just definition of Nirvana
in the malapa mezzo-soprano us my trails
definition of nirvana
well isn't me under negative emotions my
looper means all of them Bamba means
stop them forever social tango because
you saw the four truths one by one after
you saw emptiness directly okay that's
the definition of Nirvana you have to
see emptiness directly you have to see
the four truth directly to to reach
nirvana otherwise it's impossible and
according to Buddhism I'll tell you I'm
going to go to DCI language okay and
tell you understand the two husband's in
the kitchen it's impossible to stop
anger impossible not possible you can
lower it you can when you can't suppress
it but you can't get rid of it until you
understand the two husband in the
kitchen not possible impossible okay and
then enlightenment is basically knowing
all things mr. know-it-all which I
achieved long ago but not enlightenment
and just kidding then you have ultimate
capacity to help other people because
you can make as many bodies as you want
at the same time okay
you can be in LA and beijing at the same
time and help people on the bus at the
same time okay then the path which is
mainly the LA River okay what we're
studying all right now what I would like
to go into is the sixteen parts of the
fortress for each and the way I would
like to do it is I'm gonna teach it to
you from two different scriptures there
just as a sampler I'll teach it to you
from two different scriptures by two
very good Lamas okay
and I'll teach you what they say Papa
one is pop uncle one is I think a deep J
and I'll teach you how they explained it
the sixteenth in the scriptures okay and
then I'm going to teach it to you based
on my own experience and what happened
to me and and I believe it's the correct
explanation of what the sixteen are okay
so normally I don't put in my own ideas
but it's difficult to find in the
scripture that the sixteen are there the
names are there there's a little
explanation about them but not much not
enough so then I'll give you are
connected to the actual experience okay
so we'll do that in this evening's class
in addition to starting our lamb rim
review which will go on for two years
and and then we'll be done with the
lahrman when we're done with the review
and then for dessert we'll do about I
don't know five or ten years of chunk up
on emptiness yeah okay
[Music]